A Guide to the Joseph H. Willits Papers FA054
Rockefeller Archive Center
Joseph H. Willits papers
1915-1969, bulk 1954-1965
1954-1965
Rockefeller Archive Center
Willits, Joseph Henry
Rockefeller Foundation
FA054
14.44 Cubic Feet 38 document cases
Arrangement note
This collection has been arranged in six series:
Series 1 - General File
Series 2 - National Bureau of Economic Research
Series 3 - The Educational Survey
Series 4 - "Excellence and Mediocrity in Colleges and Universities"
Series 5 - Armonk and Byram Hills Schools
Series 1039 - Photographs
Biographical/Historical note
Joseph Henry Willits was born on June 16, 1889, in Ward, Pennsylvania. His family traced itself back to early Quaker settlers; as a sign of his heritage, Willits himself often used the "plain speech" in correspondence with his co-religionists and older relatives.
Willits received his A.B. in 1911 and his A.M. in 1912 from Swarthmore College. In the latter year he was appointed Instructor of Geography and Industrial Economics at the Wharton School of Finance and Economics of the University of Pennsylvania. He received his Ph.D. in Economics from that university in 1916. During World War I, Willits served as an employment supervisor of the U.S. Naval Aircraft Factory in Philadelphia. After the war he returned to the University of Pennsylvania; in 1921 he was promoted to Director of the Department of Industrial Economics at the Wharton School, later becoming Dean of the School (1933-1939).
During this period, Dr. Willits served on a number of Federal advisory boards and was active as a copious writer and speaker on labor problems. In 1928 he delivered the Wertheim Lectures at Harvard. He was elected President of the National Bureau of Economic Research in 1933 and Executive Director from 1936 to 1939. He retained ties with this organization until 1968.
From January 1, 1939, until his retirement on June 30, 1954, Dr. Willits was Director of the Division of Social Sciences of The Rockefeller Foundation.
After his retirement from the Foundation, Dr. Willits was named Director of The Educational Survey of the University of Pennsylvania. Under his direction and coordination, every major facet of university life came under review. This massive project was completed between 1954-1959. Dr. Willits conducted a similar study of the Winterthur Museum in 1961.
Partially financed by the Carnegie Corporation, Dr. Willits worked on a general study of "Excellence and Mediocrity in Colleges and Universities" which was one of his principal activities during the 1960s. Although the completed manuscript and its several revisions were submitted to publishers, this work never appeared in print.
Dr. Willits was married twice: on May 3, 1913, to Ruth Clement Sharp (died February 26, 1961), by whom he had three children; and on August 28, 1962, to Therese Spockman Barclay. Dr. Willits died on October 16, 1979.
Scope and Contents note
The Joseph H. Willits Papers will be of interest to the historian of social science and education in the United States. Dr. Willits's keen interest in the quality of academic life is amply documented in his correspondence and manuscripts. The papers focus on Dr. Willits's years after his retirement from The Rockefeller Foundation in 1954 and include correspondence and reports relating to The Educational Survey (1954-1959) and his work on the manuscript "Excellence and Mediocrity in Colleges and Universities" (1961-1969). Approximately one-sixth of this collection refers to his pre-retirement career: this portion (mostly in Series 1) includes speeches, correspondence, and reports generated from his association with the Wharton School and The Rockefeller Foundation. Personal correspondence, however, has been scantily preserved.
Subjects include economics, Rockefeller Foundation policy, academic life, and Quaker activities.
Correspondents include Chester I. Barnard, Nora Beeson, Norman S. Buchanan, Arthur E. Burns, Raymond B. Fosdick, Gaylord P. Harnwell, Harold A. Innis, Malcolm Preston, Dean Rusk, Carl O. Sauer, J. Russell Smith, and E. B. Wilson.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for researchare noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Separated Materials
A set of four reverse blueprints, entitled "Proposed Alterations to Whippoorwill School, Armonk, NY," February 16, 1961, has been removed to the map case.
Related Archival Materials note
Related material may be found in the Rockefeller Foundation Archives, Record Group 2 - General Correspondence, Series 100 - International, Willits, for the years 1939-1954. Dr. Willits's correspondence as Director of the Division of Social Sciences is scattered throughout the Project Files (Record Groups 1.1 and 1.2).
File Plan note
Former Classification: IV 2A 39
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Joseph H. Willits Papers were donated to The Rockefeller Archive Center on April 9, 1980, by Therese S. B. Willits, his widow, and Robin Dana Willits, his son.
Economics; Education; Social sciences; United States
- General File, 1915-1969; 1
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged according to Dr. Willits's original alphabetical filing order; loose papers discovered in the course of processing have been interfiled.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of correspondence, reports, and other documents. Included in these papers is material related to Dr. Willits's early career with the University of Pennsylvania, a file of his speeches, memoranda, and reports generated as Director of the Division of Social Sciences of the Rockefeller Foundation, the 1961 study of the Winterthur Museum, family papers, and personal correspondence.
  - Academic Freedom, 1946-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barnard, Chester I., 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Buchanan, Norman S., 1947-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - C (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Council of Corporate Executives on Contributions, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - D-F (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Family, 1939-1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fosdick, Raymond B., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Foundations and Their Policies, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - H (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Innis, Harold A., 1940-1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Innis, Harold A., 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - K (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - L (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters from Abroad, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Morgan, Dr. Arthur E., 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - N (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Poley, Irvin, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Preston, Malcolm, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Publications, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Orders.
  - Quaker Material, 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Robbins, Lionel, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Conference on Economics, June 10, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Transcript.
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Memos and Reports, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Memos and Reports, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Memos and Reports, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Memos and Reports, 1950-1954 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Morals and Ethics Proposal, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, Retirement from, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Royal Bank of Canada, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Rutgers University - Extension Services, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - S (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Salem Historical Society, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Sauer, Carl O., 1943-1954 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Selectmen of Jackson, New Hampshire, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Sharples, Isaac, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    1887 statement.
  - Smith, Claude (Duane, Morris & Heckscher, Legal Counsel), 1965 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Smith, J. Russell, 1945-1953 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Smith, J. Russell, 1956-1965 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - "Social Sciences in the Postwar World" - Letters from Social Scientists for a Symposium (A-M), 1945 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - "Social Sciences in the Postwar World" - Letters from Social Scientists for a Symposium (N-Z), 1945 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Social Science Research Council, 1939-1949 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Social Science Research Council, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Source File - Quotations (A-Z and Anonymous) (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Source File - Reprints, 1951-1955 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Source File - Speeches (A-D) (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Source File - Speeches (F-I) (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Source File - Speeches (J-M) (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Source File - Speeches (R-T) (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Source File - Speeches (W-Z) (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Speeches, 1920-1931 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Speeches, 1933-1934 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Speeches, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Speeches, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Speeches, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Speeches, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Speeches, 1939-1954 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Speeches - Undated Notes and Catalogue (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Sunday Breakfast Club, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Swarthmore College - Board of Managers, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Swarthmore College - Board of Managers, 1967-1969 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Swarthmore College - Courtesy Tickets, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Swarthmore College - Miscellany, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Teachers' Insurance Annuity Association, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Terry, Jesse E., 1964-1966 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Town Club, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - University of Pennsylvania, 1915-1920, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - University of Pennsylvania - Board of Trustees, 1959, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - University of Pennsylvania - Presidential Search, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Wages, 1927-1948 (Box 7, Folder 71)
    Bibliography, reprints, notes.
  - Walton, George, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Warren, Robert T., 1939-1944 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Warren, Robert T., 1946-1950 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Wharton School of Finance and Economics, 1929-1938 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Wharton School of Finance and Economics, 1946-1949 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Wharton School of Finance and Economics, 1950-1954 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Wharton School of Finance and Economics, 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Wharton School of Finance and Economics, 1957-1967 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Winterthur Museum Study, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Wilson, E. B., 1942, 1956-1959 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Wistar Parties, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Worden and Risberg Company, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - The Workroom - New York Monthly Meeting, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Yeagle, Vivian, 1964-1965 (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Young, Donald, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 86)
- National Bureau of Economic Research, 1934-1968; 2
  This series consists of correspondence, internal and published papers, and reports. Of special interest is the transcript of a conference Dr. Willits chaired in 1934. The material in this series dates primarily from the early 1960s.
  - Annual Meetings - Board of Directors, September 30, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 87)
    Agenda and notes.
  - Annual Meetings - Board of Directors, September 30, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - Annual Reports, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - Booklets, 1960-1962 (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - Conference, March 4, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 91)
    Transcript of meetings chaired by Dr. Willits, featuring a speech by E. E. Day with discussion.
  - Correspondence and Reports, 1936-1947 (Box 10, Folder 92)
  - Correspondence and Reports, 1961-1968 (Box 10, Folder 93)
  - Director Search - Correspondence and Reports, 1964-1965 (Box 10, Folder 94)
  - Director Search - Interviews - Notes, 1964-1965 (Box 10, Folder 95)
  - Director Search - Interviews - Notebooks, 1964-1965 (Box 10, Folder 96)
  - Director Search - Interviews - Notebooks, 1964-1965 (Box 10, Folder 97)
  - Executive Papers, 1960-1961 (Box 11, Folder 98)
  - Executive Papers, 1960-1961 (Box 11, Folder 99)
  - Financial Reports, 1960-1961 (Box 11, Folder 100)
  - Financial Reports, 1961-1963 (Box 11, Folder 101)
  - Papers - Dickinson, Frank G. - "Philanthropies and Public Policy", 1961 (Box 11, Folder 102)
  - Papers - Friedman, Milton - "The Interpolation of Time Series by Related Factors", 1962 (Box 11, Folder 103)
  - Papers - Goldsmith, Raymond W. - "The National Wealth of the United States", 1961 (Box 12, Folder 104)
  - Papers - Goldsmith, Raymond W. - "The National Wealth of the United States" - Appendix, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 105)
  - Papers - Hane, George - "United States Savings Bonds Program", 1961 (Box 12, Folder 106)
  - Papers - Kahn, C. Harry - "Unincorporated Enterprise Under the Income Tax", 1962 (Box 12, Folder 107)
  - Papers - Kaufman, Adam - "Small-Scale Industry in the Soviet Union", 1961 (Box 12, Folder 108)
  - Papers - Selden, Richard T. - "The Postwar Rise in the Velocity of Money", 1961 (Box 13, Folder 109)
  - Papers - Smith, Paul F. - "The Cost of Providing Consumer Credit", 1962 (Box 13, Folder 110)
  - Papers - Stigler, George J. - "Capital and Rates of Return", 1962 (Box 13, Folder 111)
  - Papers - Williams, Ernest W. - "Transportation in the Soviet Union", 1961 (Box 13, Folder 112)
  - Papers - Wojnilower, Albert M. - "The Quality of Bank Loans", 1962 (Box 13, Folder 113)
  - Papers - Zarnowitz, Victor - "Unfilled Orders, Price Charges, and Business Fluctuations", 1962 (Box 13, Folder 114)
  - Yntema Committee, 1968; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 14, Folder 115)
  - Yntema Committee, 1968; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 14, Folder 116)
- The Educational Survey, 1953-1959; 3
  Series 3 has been organized as follows: final summary report, correspondence, drafts and cover letters, individual departmental reports.
  This series includes the final summary report (two sets), correspondence, drafts and cover letters for individual departmental reports, and a set of those departmental reports. Dr. Willits directed this study for the University of Pennsylvania from his retirement in 1954 until its completion in 1959.
  - Final Summary Report - Set 1, Volume I (Box 14, Folder 117)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 1, Volume II (Box 14, Folder 118)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 1, Volume III (Box 14, Folder 119)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 1, Volume IVA (Box 15, Folder 120)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 1, Volume IVB (Box 15, Folder 121)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 1, Volume IVC (Box 15, Folder 122)
    With annotations and inserts.
  - Final Summary Report - Set 1, Volume VA (Box 15, Folder 123)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 1, Volume VB (Box 16, Folder 124)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 2, Volume I, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 16, Folder 125)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 2, Volume I, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 16, Folder 126)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 2, Volume II, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 16, Folder 127)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 2, Volume II, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 16, Folder 128)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 2, Volume III, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 17, Folder 129)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 2, Volume III, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 17, Folder 130)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 2, Volume IV, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 17, Folder 131)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 2, Volume IV, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 17, Folder 132)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 2, Volume V, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 17, Folder 133)
  - Final Summary Report - Set 2, Volume V, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 17, Folder 134)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box 18, Folder 135)
  - Correspondence, 1956-April 1957 (Box 18, Folder 136)
  - Correspondence, May-June 1957 (Box 18, Folder 137)
  - Correspondence, July 1957 (Box 18, Folder 138)
  - Correspondence, August-December 1957 (Box 18, Folder 139)
  - Correspondence - Trustees' Letters, 1957 (Box 18, Folder 140)
    Extracts and Interim Report on Trustees.
  - Correspondence, January-March 1958 (Box 19, Folder 141)
  - Correspondence, April-June 1958 (Box 19, Folder 142)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1958 (Box 19, Folder 143)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1959 (Box 19, Folder 144)
  - Correspondence, July-October 1959 (Box 19, Folder 145)
  - Correspondence - Report of the President - "Assaying a University", 1959 (Box 19, Folder 146)
  - Drafts and Cover Letters, 1955-1956 (Box 19, Folder 147)
  - Drafts and Cover Letters, January-July 1957 (Box 20, Folder 148)
  - Drafts and Cover Letters, August-October 1957 (Box 20, Folder 149)
  - Drafts and Cover Letters, November 1957-March 1958 (Box 20, Folder 150)
  - Drafts and Cover Letters, March-April 1958 (Box 20, Folder 151)
  - Drafts and Cover Letters, May-July 1958 (Box 20, Folder 152)
  - Drafts and Cover Letters, September-December 1958 (Box 21, Folder 153)
  - Drafts and Cover Letters, January-May 1959 (Box 21, Folder 154)
  - Drafts and Cover Letters, undated (Box 21, Folder 155)
  - Drafts and Cover Letters - Draft of Report, circa 1959 (Box 21, Folder 156)
  - Departmental Reports - Survey of the Organization and Administration, Volume I, Organization, 1954 (Box 21, Folder 157)
  - Departmental Reports - Annual Report, 1955-1956, June 30, 1956 (Box 21, Folder 158)
  - Departmental Reports - "Advanced Study and Research in the Social Sciences," (Bennett, Merrill K.), June 30, 1956 (Box 22, Folder 159)
  - Departmental Reports - "Statistics and Statistical Studies," (Koopmans, Tjalling C.), June 30, 1956 (Box 22, Folder 160)
  - Departmental Reports - "The Training of Teachers for Elementary and Secondary Education," (Robb, David M.), June 30, 1956 (Box 22, Folder 161)
  - Departmental Reports - "Humanistic Teaching and the Place of Ethical and Religious Values in Higher Education," (Aubrey, Edwin E.), September 1956 (Box 22, Folder 162)
  - Departmental Reports - "Humanistic Teaching and the Place of Ethical and Religious Values in Higher Education," (Aubrey, Edwin E.) - Draft, September 1956 (Box 22, Folder 163)
  - Departmental Reports - "Social Work Education at the University of Pennsylvania", October 15, 1956 (Box 22, Folder 164)
  - Departmental Reports - "The School of Veterinary Medicine," (Stafseth, Henrik J.), January 1957 (Box 22, Folder 165)
  - Departmental Reports - "Memoranda Relating to the Wharton Undergraduate Curriculum", February 1957 (Box 23, Folder 166)
  - Departmental Reports - "Academic Advising at the University of Pennsylvania," (Straub, Jean Spencer), July 1957 (Box 23, Folder 167)
  - Departmental Reports - "Dental Education at the University of Pennsylvania," (Fleming, Willard C.), July 1957 (Box 23, Folder 168)
  - Departmental Reports - "A Program for the Wharton School", November 1957 (Box 23, Folder 169)
  - Departmental Reports - "Graduate Study in the Humanities," (Keniston, Hayward), December 1957 (Box 24, Folder 170)
  - Departmental Reports - "School of Medicine at the University of Pennsylvania," (Coman, Dale Rex), December 1957 (Box 24, Folder 171)
  - Departmental Reports - "Undergraduate Education in the Liberal Arts and Sciences," (MacLeod, Robert B.), February 1958 (Box 24, Folder 172)
  - Departmental Reports - "Undergraduate Education in the Liberal Arts and Sciences," (MacLeod, Robert B.) - Appendix, Volume I, February 1958 (Box 24, Folder 173)
  - Departmental Reports - "Undergraduate Education in the Liberal Arts and Sciences," (MacLeod, Robert B.) - Appendix, Volume II, February 1958 (Box 24, Folder 174)
  - Departmental Reports - "Undergraduate Education in the Liberal Arts and Sciences," (MacLeod, Robert B.) - Appendix, Volume III, February 1958 (Box 25, Folder 175)
  - Departmental Reports - "The Faculty at the University of Pennsylvania," (Shyrock, Richard H.), February 1958 (Box 25, Folder 176)
  - Departmental Reports - "Financial and Budgetary Problems", February 1958 (Box 25, Folder 177)
  - Departmental Reports - "Toward an Affirmative Policy for Student Personnel", February 1958 (Box 25, Folder 178)
  - Departmental Reports - "Graduate Training and Research in the Physical Sciences", March 1958 (Box 25, Folder 179)
  - Departmental Reports - "The Engineering Schools at the University of Pennsylvania," (Pigford, Robert L., et. al.), April 1958 (Box 25, Folder 180)
  - Departmental Reports - "The Engineering Schools at the University of Pennsylvania," (Pigford, Robert L., et. al.) - Faculty Comments and Revisions, April 1958 (Box 26, Folder 181)
  - Departmental Reports - "The Wharton School of Finance and Economics," (Hettinger, Albert J., et. al.), April 1958 (Box 26, Folder 182)
  - Departmental Reports - "The Law School at the University of Pennsylvania", May 1958 (Box 26, Folder 183)
  - Departmental Reports - "The School of Fine Arts," (Young, Donald R., et. al.), May 1958 (Box 26, Folder 184)
  - Departmental Reports - "The Board of Trustees of the University of Pennsylvania," (Belcher, Donald R.), June 1958 (Box 26, Folder 185)
  - Departmental Reports - "Graduate Study and Research in the Arts and Sciences," (Keniston, Hayward), June 1958 (Box 26, Folder 186)
  - Departmental Reports - "Nursing Education," (Bridgman, Margaret, et. al), June 1958 (Box 27, Folder 187)
  - Departmental Reports - "School of Auxiliary Medical Sciences," (Crane, A. Reynolds), June 1958 (Box 27, Folder 188)
  - Departmental Reports - "Summaries of Survey Reports, Volume I", June 30, 1958 (Box 27, Folder 189)
  - Departmental Reports - "Summaries of Survey Reports, Volume II", June 30, 1958 (Box 27, Folder 190)
  - Departmental Reports - "The Division of Biological and Medical Sciences," (Hebb, D. O., et. al.), January 1959 (Box 27, Folder 191)
  - Departmental Reports - "Budget Policy of the University of Pennsylvania," (Belcher, Donald R.), May 1959 (Box 28, Folder 192)
  - Departmental Reports - "Budget Policy of the University of Pennsylvania," (Belcher, Donald R.) - Revised Copy, May 1959 (Box 28, Folder 193)
- "Excellence and Mediocrity in Colleges and Universities", 1950-1969, bulk 1960-1969; 1960-1969; 4
  Series 4 has been organized as follows: drafts of the manuscript, correspondence, source file, interviews, followed by book reviews, correspondence, and notes by Nora Beeson.
  This series includes various revised drafts of the manuscript, correspondence, a source file of bulletins, notes and clippings, and interviews conducted by Dr. Willits, followed by book reviews, correspondence and notes by his assistant, Nora Beeson. Much of this material is undated: the manuscript drafts have been arbitrarily placed in presumed order of composition based on content or change of title page. A few items marked by Dr. Willits as relating to this study have been removed to Series 1, 2, or 3, as having a closer connection to other documents included in those series.
  - Outlines, circa 1961 (Box 28, Folder 194)
  - Draft - Introduction and Chapter III (Box 28, Folder 195)
  - Draft - Chapter IV (Box 28, Folder 196)
  - Draft - Chapter V-VI (Box 28, Folder 197)
  - Draft - Chapters VII and IX (Box 28, Folder 198)
  - "Letter to a Grandson", circa 1966 (Box 28, Folder 199)
  - Draft I (Box 28, Folder 200)
    Incomplete.
  - Draft II (Box 29, Folder 201)
  - Draft III, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 29, Folder 202)
  - Draft III, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 29, Folder 203)
  - Draft IV (Box 29, Folder 204)
  - Draft V, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 29, Folder 205)
  - Draft V, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 29, Folder 206)
  - Draft VI, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 30, Folder 207)
  - Draft VI, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 30, Folder 208)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 30, Folder 209)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1969 (Box 30, Folder 210)
  - Source File - Bulletins, 1950-1956 (Box 30, Folder 211)
  - Source File - Notes and Clippings, Folder 1 of 4 (Box 30, Folder 212)
  - Source File - Notes and Clippings, Folder 2 of 4 (Box 31, Folder 213)